Guide to the Partners for Livable Communities records, 1960-2012
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Partners for Livable Communities records
1960-2012
C0230
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
78.5 linear feet (157 boxes; 3 oversize folders)
The collection consists of reports, brochures, posters, books, audio/visual materials, and newsletters. The records cover the entire history of the Partners for Livable Communities, beginning with its inception in the 1970s at the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA).
Partners for Livable Communities.
Historical Information
Partners for Livable Communities (PLC) is a national, nonprofit organization working to restore and renew American communities by providing information, leadership and guidance that help communities help themselves. Founded by a consortium of the National Endowment of the Arts in 1977 under the title "Partners for Livable Places," the organization initially focused on design and culture as resources for livability.
During the 1980s the organization expanded its scope to address the economic concerns of communities and launched a number of programs, each focusing on a specific problem area of community development. The Economics of Amenity program secured PLC's place as a national resource dedicated to the economic value of using amenities for community development. It was soon followed by three other programs - Cities in Transition, The New Civics, and Celebrate the American Community - which approached community development in a more holistic manner that took open spaces and cultural centers into consideration as well as the impact of social and physical changes to the urban landscape.
During the 1990s the Shaping Growth in America program was launched to address issues of social inequity, children and families, minorities and the poor. The 1990s also brought a new name, "Partners for Livable Communities," and a redefinition of the Partners' Resource Center as the National Center for Community Action. PLC continues to work toward the growth and improvement of American communities to this day.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Partners for Livable Communities in 2012.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of reports, brochures, posters, books, audio/visual materials, and newsletters. The records cover the entire history of the Partners for Livable Communities, beginning with its inception in the 1970s at the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA). The majority of the collection is comprised of primary resources (research, reports, correspondence, meeting minutes, photographs, audio/visual materials, etc.), which relate to projects that Partners for Livable Communities has undertaken during the past 33 years of its existence. These materials are important for understanding how the Livable Cities Act has developed over the years from its inception in 1978 to the present. They document how Partners moved from a granting agency (when it was associated with the NEA) to an independent, non-profit organization focused on initiating important programs and projects of its own, many of which have resulted in major changes in the quality of design and living in urban environments in the United States. The collection is also important because Partners prepared the groundwork for many key initiatives including model legislation, the Livable Communities Act of 2009, which is currently under consideration by the Obama administration. Materials in the collection will help researchers to understand the development of city planning over the past 30+ years in the United States, as well as the best practices, standards and policies that have been advanced by Partners. A preliminary inventory is available.
Series 1, Amenity Resources & Quality of Life, the largest of the collection, contains resources used in Partner's first program, The Economics of Amenity. These materials are focused around the economic value of design, cultural amenities, and the impact on the quality of life in a community. This series includes pamphlets, binders, and books on Partners for Livable Communities' Creative City initiative, notes on sponsored charrettes in Kingsport and Memphis, Tennessee; Alexandria and Roanoke, Virginia; Glendale and San Buenaventura California; and Baltimore, Maryland. Other resources in this series include documentation on the importance of quality design and regional publications produced and gathered by PLC and other private organizations in the United States and Europe.
Series 2, Community Development, contains resources gathered by Partners for Livable Communities relevant to their various initiatives and programs. Specifically, they collected a variety of books, binders, reports, and articles, published by Partners and other outside organizations, that focus on cultural and community planning, including PLC's Aging in Place initiative, a small portion of the Livability Clearinghouse, notes taken in the Columbus, Ohio; Hartford, Connecticut; and Kingsport, Tennessee charrettes and the materials on the selections for the America's Most Livable City awards, sponsored by Partners of Livable Communities.
Series 3, Culture Builds Community, contains the gathered resources for the long-term initiative, started in 1993. The goal of this initiative is to use certain cultural assets to build a community's economy, community pride, and the quality of life. Included in this series are various workbooks, papers, presentations, and binders collected that focus on cultural assets and it affects the growth of the surrounding communities. Some specific records include a collection of PLC's "Connections" newsletter, various charrettes that took place in Kansas City, Missouri, and documentation on the importance of libraries, art, schools, and markets in a community.
Series 4, New Civics, contains four subseries, Benchmarks and Indices, Leadership for Change, Regional Strategies, and Visioning and Local Participation that focus on developing successful leadership strategies to create community-centered programs through a cooperative effort between local government and private businesses. Some specific resources include the collection of documentation gathered during the various charrettes and workshops held in Frederick, Maryland; San Diego, California; Arlington, Virginia; and Grand Rapids, Michigan, the programs from the Bridge Builders ceremonies, the Dublin Community Plans, the Indiana Cities Conference, and other regionally-focused reports.
Series 5, Partners Resources, includes the materials necessary for the workings and advertising of Partners of Livable Communities and its affiliates throughout the United States. Specifically, this series includes the extensive collection of PLACE newsletters, various directories from 1975 to 2011, information on the Board of Trustees in 2002, the pamphlets from America's Most Livable Cities and the Visions and Community Spirit Awards, informative handouts written about Partners and its various initiatives, the Biannual Activities reports, and various regional reports written for Partners for Livable Communities.
Series 6, Shared Heritage of the Americas contains information that looks at the special resources inherent throughout North America, Central America, and the Caribbean. This small series contains various books, binders, magazines, transcripts, and reports that explore the archaeology, history, and physical geography of these rich regions. Specific resources include PLC's research effort for an article about underwater archaeology and documentation from two forums that focused on preservation throughout the Americas.
Series 7, Tourism: Heritage, Discovery, & Ecotourism, includes materials focused on the importance of conservation and tourism development. Like with Series 5 (Shared Heritage with the Americas), this series focuses on responsible tourism using the available resources in a region. It also includes information on healthy tourism growth and conservation. Specific resources include the information gathered during the African-American Museum of Delaware Charratte, the Tourism Task Force for Greater Cincinnati Report, and the Travel Review Conference proceedings.
Series 8 consists of photogaphs that document the activities of Partners from the 1970s through 2010s. Subjects include events hosted by Partners, images of commuity activities in cities, and pictures of the Partners staff.
Series 9 contains audiovisual materials. There are a variety of videotapes, cassettes, compact discs and diskettes that Partners created and gathered. Most of the materials are relevant to the various sponsored programs that Partners of Livable Communities initiated. Some specific audio and visual materials includes CDs of photos from various Partners-hosted events, video and audio documentation of regional charrettes and meetings, and back-up diskettes of various articles and documents that PLC's employees authored.
Series 10 contains oversized materials. Most of these resources are posters created for Partners' various programs, regional newspaper articles focused on community growth, and large books published by various private companies.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Arrangement
Organized into ten series.
Series 1: Amenity Resources/Quality of Life, 1973-2011 (Boxes 1-38)
Series 2: Community Development, 1960-2011 (Boxes 39-62)
Series 3: Culture Builds Community, 1978-2012 (Boxes 63-86)
Series 4: New Civics, 1974-2012 (Boxes 86-111)
Series 5: Partners' Resources, 1967-2012 (Boxes 111-131)
Series 6: Shared Heritage of the Americas, 1982-1995 (Boxes 131-135)
Series 7: Tourism: Heritage, Discovery, and Ecotourism, 1979-2008 (Boxes 135-143)
Series 8: Photographs, 1970s-2010s
Series 9: Audiovisual, 1977-2011 (Boxes 144-154)
Series 10: Oversized, 1973-2008 (Boxes 155-157)
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the that contains publications on many subjects related to community renewal and planning.
Index Terms:
Corporate Names:
Partners for Livable Communities.
Subjects:
Buildings--Remodeling for other use--United States.; Central business districts--United States.; Open spaces--United States.; Tourism--United States.; Transportation--United States--Planning.
Contents List
- Series 1: Amenity Resources/Quality of Life, 1973-2011; (38 boxes)
  Series 1, the largest of the collection, contains resources used in Partner's first program, The Economics of Amenity. These materials are focused around the economic value of design, cultural amenities, and the impact on the quality of life in a community.
  - Action by Design, Facilitating Design Decisions into the 21st Century, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amenities and Community Futures, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amenities and Economic Development: A Conceptual Framework, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amenities and Your Community Futures, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amenity Strategies in Cities - Common Themes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Arts, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - An Enhancement Strategy for New York's Fashion District, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Animation of the City, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    folder 1 of 3
  - Animation of the City, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    folder 2 of 3
  - Animation of the City, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    folder 3 of 3
  - Animation: The Breath of Life for American Cities, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anti-littering in Pittsburgh Research, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Arkansas: Its Heritage. A Plan of Action, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    folder 1 of 2
  - Arkansas: Its Heritage. A Plan of Action, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    folder 2 of 2
  - Arlington County Arts and Humanities Advisory Committee Final Report to the County Board, Arlington, VA, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art in Public Places, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Art in the Economic Life of the City, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art Means Business Conference Papers, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Art of Celebration, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Art of City Design, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Art of Landscape Architecture, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Art of Regeneration: Conference Papers, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Art of the City: Cultural Industry and Urban Revitalization, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Artists' Housing: Creating Live/Work Space that Lasts, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Arts & The Economy, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Arts and City Planning, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Arts and Entertainment Districts, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    folder 1 or 2
  - Arts and Entertainment Districts, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Arts Edge: Places and Space for the Arts in Civic Economics, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Arts in a Living Downtown: Best Practices, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Arts in a Living Downtown: Best Practices, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Arts in a Living Downtown: The Next Steps; Final Report to the Federal City Council, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Arts Space and Economic Development Experience in Six Cities, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Arts Space and Economic Development Experience in Six Cities, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Arts Space and Economic Development Experience in Six Cities, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Assessing Scenic Development Highway Strategy in Southern Indiana, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Background paper on the Benefits of Amenity - "Invest in These and You Get This", 2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Baltimore Brewery Charrette, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Branding Charrette, Roanoke, Virginia, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Building by Design Workshop, Illinois Arts Council, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    folder 1 of 4
  - Building by Design Workshop, Illinois Arts Council, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    folder 2 of 4
  - Building by Design Workshop, Illinois Arts Council, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    folder 3 of 4
  - Building by Design Workshop, Illinois Arts Council, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    folder 4 of 4
  - Business and the Arts from a Mutual Need of Working Partnerships, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Changing Times for the Values of Amenity, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - City As A Stage, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - City Assets Program Resource and Publication Roster, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - City Assets: Quality of Life in the Economic Life of the City Narration Script, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - City Building - A Place for the Arts and Mixed Use Developments: Models for Public-Private Partnership, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Civic Movement: Green, Smart, and Fair, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Clearinghouse Research on Adaptive Reuse of Theaters as Cultural Facilities, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Communications as Engagement: Communications Strategy for Revitalization, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Community Design: Six Case Studies of Revitalization, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Community Futures and Quality of Life, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Competitive Edge Conference, Chattanooga, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Competitive Edge Conference, Chattanooga, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Connecting Heritage to The Future: New Life for Old Building in African American Communities, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Connecting Heritage to The Future: New Life for Old Building in African American Communities, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Creative Cities Working Meeting #1 - May 23, 2001 - Washington DC (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Creative City Anthology, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Creative City Binder, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Creative City Charrette, City of San Buenaventura, December 9-10, 2002, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Creative City News, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Creative City: Power for the New Economy Resource Paper, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Creative City: Power of the New Economy, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Creative City: Working Paper on Key Themes and Issues, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Creative City: Year One, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Creativity in the Evolving Workforce: a Creative Cities Thought Paper, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Cultivating Creative Communities, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Cultural Development Strategy - Towards a Cultural Policy for Brisbane, Australia, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Districts: Buffalo, Dallas, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Rochester, and Cleveland, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    folder 1 of 5
  - Cultural Districts: Buffalo, Dallas, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Rochester, and Cleveland, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    folder 2 of 5
  - Cultural Districts: Buffalo, Dallas, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Rochester, and Cleveland, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    folder 3 of 5
  - Cultural Districts: Buffalo, Dallas, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Rochester, and Cleveland, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    folder 4 of 5
  - Cultural Districts: Buffalo, Dallas, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Rochester, and Cleveland, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    folder 5 of 5
  - Cultural Facilities and Mixed-Use Development, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Cultural Facilities and Mixed-Use Development, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Cultural Plan for Jondalup City: a New Town Outside of Perth, Australia, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    folder 1 of 6
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    folder 2 of 6
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    folder 3 of 6
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    folder 4 of 6
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    folder 5 of 6
  - Cultural Plan: City of Elkhart, Indiana, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    folder 6 of 6
  - Cultural Planning, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Cultural Planning Group Report, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Cultural Planning Handbook: An Essential Australian Guide, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Planning--Catalysts for a Greater Cleveland, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Cultural Planning: A Prospective for Small Towns, A Case Study of Frederick, Maryland, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Dark Star Park of Arlington County, VA, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Design America, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Design Art and Architecture in Transportation, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Design Arts 2: Places and Spaces for the Arts, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Design Arts in America: A Working Session of the National Endowment for the Arts, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Design Competition Manual, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Design Competition Manual II, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Design Competition Manual III: A Guide for Sponsors, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Design Considerations: Barrier-Free Access Design Competitions, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Design Guidelines: An Annotated Bibliography, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Design Information Exchange: An Interim Report, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Design Necessity: A Casebook of Federally Initiated Projects, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Design Research, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Design Research, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Developing a Cultural Plan - St. Paul, Minnesota: A Strategy for Arts, Culture and Entertainment, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Downtown Alive: A Workshop to Spark a Spirited Washington DC, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Downtown Public Spaces: Business and Governmental Partnerships: Case Studies in New York State, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - East Harbor Charrette Report and Preliminary Materials, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Economics of Amenity Binder, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Economics of Amenity Binder, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Economics of Amenity in the United States of America, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Economics of Amenity: Community Futures and Quality of Life, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Design Research Topics: Methods and Values, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Exemplary Design Research 1983: Results of the Design Research Recognition Program, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Fact Sheets Prepared for the Arts Edge Conference, Pittsburgh, PA, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Feasibility Study for Renovation of the Old Post Office, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Federal Architecture: A Framework for Debate, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Federal Architecture: Adaptive Use Facilities, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Federal Architecture: Adaptive Use Facilities, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Federal Architecture: Multiple Use Facilities, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Federal Architecture: Multiple Use Facilities, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Federal Architecture: Multiple Use Facilities, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Federal Design Library - Grids: Their Meaning and Use for Federal Designers, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Federal Design Matters, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Federal Presence: Artchitecture, Politics, and Symbols in United States Governement Building, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Federal Regional Design Assembly of Western States, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Federal Spaces Community Places, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Final Report to the German Marshall Fund: Survey of the European Experience in Design and Management of Urban Public Spaces, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Final Report to the German Marshall Fund: Survey of the European Experience in Design and Management of Urban Public Spaces, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Final Report to the German Marshall Fund: Survey of the European Experience in Design and Management of Urban Public Spaces, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Footnotes Number 1: Handbook for Pedestrian Action, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Footnotes Number 2: Rediscovery of the Pedestrian, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Footnotes Number 3: Banning the Car Downtown, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Footnotes Number 4: American Urban Malls, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Fort Dickinson Park/Knoxville, Tennessee, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Forum on Public Architecture/Conference for Governors and Administrators: A Resource Book, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Forum on Public Architecture/Conference for Governors and Administrators: A Resource Book, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Fourth Federal Design Assembly, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Frey Foundation Public Art Placemaking Project Final Report, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Frey Foundation Public Art Placemaking Project Final Report, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Frey Foundation Public Art Placemaking Project Final Report, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Frey Foundation Public Art Placemaking Project Final Report, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - From Commas to Cathedrals - Design at Work, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Funding Sources for Architectural Programs, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Greater Philadelphia's Competitive Edge: The Nonprofit Cultural Industry and its Economic Value to the Region, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Greater Portland:1990; Keeping Livability in Mind, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Guide to Great American Public Places: A Journey of Discovery, Learning and Delight in the Public Realm, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Guide to Great American Public Places: A Journey of Discovery, Learning and Delight in the Public Realm, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Hanks Institute Feasibility Study, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Hanks Institute Feasibility Study, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Historic Shipwrecks: Issues in Management, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Historic Shipwrecks: Issues in Management, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Historic Shipwrecks: Issues in Management, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Historic Shipwrecks: Issues in Management, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Historic Shipwrecks: Issues in Management, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - In Collaboration: Artists on the Metro Design Team - A Practical Handbook, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Insights on Sites: Perspectives on Art in Public Places, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Issues in Supporting the Arts, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Issues in Urban Archaeology, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Joondalup City Centre and Cultural Facilities, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Kayaking, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 1)